PROJECT LOCATION
City of banning & City of Cabazon
● 1st location: i-10 interchange in Banning: Ramsey Street
○ EB Off ramp to Ramsey St
○ Currently only access for EB On-Ramp and Off-Ramp
● 2nd Location: Main St near Dinosaur Restaurant
○ Hook Ramp EB/WB On-Ramp and Off-Ramp
○ Hook hybrid ramp on ramp: has an adjacent interchange (non-conventional)
● 3rd Location: New Interchange near Morongo Casino and Cabazon Outlets (May not
have enough time to study this location)
○ Lots of operational issues
○ Had a stop sign then roundabout and still has operational issue
■ Roundabout causing backup on freeway
○ Look into if another interchange is possible in this location
○ About 2 miles apart from Main St to Morongo Area

PROJECT DETAILS
● Interchange improvement project at two existing interchanges
○ Ramsey Interchange (Banning)
○ Main St interchange (Cabazon)
New interchange between Indian Truck Trail and Main St

● Evaluate the operations at adjacent interchanges
○ Hargrave St
○ Malki Rd
○ Apache Trail
○ Haugen-Lehmann Way
● I-10 built mainly for military
● Consider greenhouse gases (SB743)
○ Affects intetrchanes bc it adds capacity
■ What’s mitigation plan then if adding capacity
● Bike lanes, park and ride, etc.
■ Goal not capacity increasing

CUSTOMER
● Professor: Dr. Yongping Zhang
● Caltrans: Justine Niu and Jason Callado
● Local Agency – City of Banning, City of Cabazon
○ Ask the cities about what is getting built or planned in the next months-years
● Users
○ Motorists, non-motorists, animals, pedestrians, cyclists, etc.
● Special groups (ie. Morongo Tribe)
○ Sensitive! Tribes have lots of power with their land
○ Morongo Band of Mission Indians
● Community

08/25/23 2

RESOURCES
● Riverside County Planning Department - General Plans (Pass Area Plan)
● Caltrans I-10 Transportation Concept Report - District 8
○ Possible resource
● City of Banning General Plan
DATA
● Drone data at Main St and Ramsey St
○ Raw data will be given from caltrans and dtm data with some elevation
○ If elevation not provided use Google
● DGN - Alignment, Existing RW, Topo
● DGN - existing Utility
● Collision data - use Transportation Injury Mapping System aka TIMS
DELIVERABLES
● Schedule
○ 1 year
● Project Study Report (PSR)
● Preliminary Environmental Analysis Report (PEAR)
● Geometric Approval Drawing (GAD)
● Advanced Planning Study (APS)
● Traffic Studies (including Traffic Analysis, HSM, and ICE)
● Website
● Public Service Video
● Augmented reality/Virtual reality (AR/VR)
TEAMS
● 2 PMs
● Environmental needs a lead
● Traffic needs a lead
● 3 Design Team: each needs a lead
PRESENTATIONS
● Caltrans District 8 Management - April 2024
● CPP CE Symposium
● Caltrans Design Management Board
○ All design managers throughout entire state of CA
● ACEC/Caltrans Professional Liaison meeting
○ Between Caltrans and local agencies/consultants
○ Usually not a Friday
● Other presentations (ITE and more)
FUTURE CALTRANS MEETINGS
● Approx. every other week
● Project topics (1 hr CT presentation, 1 hr project update)
● Guest presentations
● Next meeting 9/1/23 @ 10:00AM Overview
○ Purpose and need

08/25/23 3

○ PDT and schedule
○ Alumni advice
■ MAKE SURE TO GET CONTACT

● Homework
○ Read General plans and other planning resources
○ Get familiar with area and constraints
■ Parallel to I-10 there’s a railway
● Railway has a larger say
● UPR challenging consider issues and how to negotiate
○ How to purchase easement (usually at least 2 years to
make a deal)

○ Look into moronogo study on transportation in area if published
○ Look how they did it in Ontario
○ Schedule
■ Add construction begin/add
■ PA&ED phase
● Could take 1-2 years which can affect PS&E and construction
phase

■ Consider how long getting easements, RW, etc.
○ See what’s in the area
● ACTION ITEMS
○ GoogleDrive given

KAT’S NOTES
● Roundabout on east side and west side entrances
● Is there an opportunity to create another interchange?
● Interchange spacing: Enough room (good amount of spacing)
○ About 1 mile for urban area
○ Is it urban or rural
○ It's about 2 miles right now
● Not studying the roundabouts - not enough time or resources
● Look into capacity of roundabout from main st to morongo
○ No geometric design
○ Maybe just conceptual
○ Look into traffic
● How to measure interstate spacing
○ From center of bridge
○ West to east
