Start: 8:52pm

everyone gets an exception for the career fair happening soon.
Purpose and Needs:
The best sections for unofficial purpose and needs will be highlighted. Each team lead chooses their contributions to purpose and need. A real purpose is around 3 bullet points / 1 sentence.
The purpose and need will be completed by Thursday 11:59pm.

In terms of attendance, 3 excused absences are allowed. (4 per semester). This applies only to the PDT meetings. If a greater number of excused attendences are required, send an email to both PMs with [SPLEAD] in the subject line. 

Sub-meetings are under the lead jurisdiction. Email the lead if you need exceptions.

Missing deadlines without excuse:
First warning -> PMs will talk with the person in question.
Future warnings -> The person will get a strike.

On Workloads:
If you give advance warning (>24hrs), then it is not considered a strike.
Punching above your weight class have consequenses depending on the lead. 
Rules for progress submitted to Caltrans and Zhang will follow a lead-wide format. 

General Deadline Rules:
Considerations -
It depends on the size of the sub-project. 1-wk before project completion, a marker or notification to the lead should be submitted. "Let me know by" dates should be attached to the assignment. "Let me know if completeable" is also attached to the assignment. Each lead decides on what is appropiate for the marks. 

Deliverable-Based Project Delivery:
The PMs will handle the milestone marks and completions dates. The Leads will handle the sub-tasks to assign to their groups. 
Team members report to team leads.
Team leads report to PMs by email.
PMs will report to advisors. When talking to advisors, CC the PMs.

Zhang should have a meeting with all the leads to talk about the project standards. 

Project Schedule:
Incase Caltrans asks about the schedule, we have a rough schedule yoinked from previous year. 
Email has been sent to Morongo.
Canvas is a tool used by the team leads. 
Deliverable based submission.

Canvas will be created, but it is up to leads to use it or not.
ALL TRAFFIC SOFTWARE ARE URGENT. 
EXISTING TOPO AND GEOMETRIC DATA ARE URGENT.
For every team, there should be a minimum deliverable in case the optimal deliverable cannot be created. 

Traffic:
Caltrans wants to calc LOS for Ped Bikes. What they are doing now, is to calc safety, volume, infrastructure score.
The conventional method of decision making is not grounded in data and is heavily flawed. 
In terms of the safety, ideally we want to be the best. Be reasonable.
Travel time reliability is how to recover from the worst case for each month.
On VMT, we are going to be above on each alternative. Caltrans will never build this. We need to prepare a deliverable on why VMTs are increasing.
Leading Pedestrian Interval (LPI) - When the ped goes first and the cars will get green later. This is usually a delta of 3 seconds. Every intersection that caltrans touches must impliment a LPI. 
We may need to tell the advisors about the LPI bill. 

Design:
QA/QC - When going over major design revisions, hand off "fast track" checklist and design file to other design team. This is to get a fresh set of eyes onto the QC process. 

Adjorned: 10:16pm