
Project Location: City of Banning & City of Cabazon
interchange 1: Located right at the end of Banning. In this interchange, there's no west-bound ramp. This is an incomplete interchange.
Goal: Turn this incomplete interchange into a complete interchange.

interchange 2: Called Main Street. 

interchange 3: New interchange. Two round-abouts in the east and west-bound ramps. Seems to have many operational issues. Stop signs didn't work. Standard round-abouts didn't work. We are planning on removing this interchange? The city is looking into it. The round-about is causing back-up onto the freeway. See figure 1 for reference between interchange 2 and interchange 1.

My customers: professor, Caltrans, Local Agency, Users, Special Groups, Community.
- Special Groups: Morongo Band of Mission Indians

Resources: 
- Riverside County Planning Department General Plans
- Caltrans I-10 Transportation Concept Report
- City of Banning General Plan

Data: 
- Drone data at Main Street and Ramsey Street (Raw Data)
- DGN - Alignment, Existing R/W, Topo
- DGN - Existing Utility
- Collision Data - use transportation injury mapping system aka TIMS

Deliverables:
- schedule
- Project study report (PRS)
- Preliminary Environmental Analysis Report (PEAR)
- Geometric Approval Drawing (GAD)
- Advanced Planning
- etc..

Presentations:
- Caltrans Disctrict 8 Management April 2024
- Cal Poly Pomona Civil Engineering Symposium
- Caltrans Design Management Board (BIG)
- ACEC Caltrans Professional Liaison meeting
- Other Presentations

Next Meeting is 23/09/01.
- Purpose and Need, PDT and schedule, Alumni Advice.

Homework:
- Read general Plans and other planning resources. Get familiar with the area and constraints. 

Team Meetings:
Project Development Team (PDT) meetings.
	Multidiscipline
	Guide project
	Coordination
	Identify Deliverables
	Monitor/track project status
	Conflict Resolution

Responsibilities:
All -
	Document Decisions
Project Managers -
	Facilitate meetings 
	Agenda
	Meeting Minutes
	Monitor the schedule
	Identify action items (who what when)
Team Leads -
	Know the schedule
	update the PMs on the project status
	share needed information
	provide guidance and solutions
	follow up with the action items
Functional Team Members - 
	know the schedule
	share ideas and concerns
	meet your deadlines
	Participate
	update team lead on progress of work

Caltrans is going to convert area to urban area. Therefore, 1 mile distance between interchange is okay.
Called to Order: 10:00am

We went over who is in each design lead group
Jasper mentioned the truck stop to Dr. Zhang
Dr. Zhang would like for the whole group to learn how to use the software. We are not going to be going into the same precision as needed in the real world. This is because we are not Caltrans engineers. This is a school project. This project is in the preliminary phase (30% of actual design). 
Purpose and Need:
Increase the flow of traffic on the freeway.
Decrease congestion on the on and off ramps.
For Ramsey, add east-bound on-ramp access and west-bound off-ramp access. This may not be doable.
Please see the purpose and need from the previous projects if you are lost about what is a purpose and need.
Purpose is what is happening now.
Need is why we are going to need it after this project is complete.
Caltrans do not want to focus on increasing capacity. 
Coachella has been booming and in the future, development will continue.
If congestion is bad, then queue lengths will extend into the mainline. This is a safety hazard.
Purpose and need will be going to multiple revisions. The main ideas should not change past the first month.
There will be a sheet for purpose and need suggestions. The deadline will be announced on discord and email. The deadline is Monday 11:59pm. 
All the senior project data can be found on the google drive. This may be direct files or links. 
Emails will be primarily sent through your cpp email.

To Install Bluebeam:
1. Search: bluebeam academic program (https://www.bluebeam.com/community/academic/#getInvolved)
1. Click on the "Apply Now" button.
2. The Anticipated Graduation Date should be 05/31/2024
3. The academic department is "Engineering"
4. The 'I'll be using REVU for a..' is "Required for a course/module"
5. The comment is, "I'll be using Bluebeam for my senior capstone project for design sheets and traffic documents."
6. All the other fields should be filled out honestly.
7. Submit the form.

Zhang approves of the use of OpenRoads as of this meeting.
Chatgpt is really useful to help learn software. 
When emailing the PMs, email BOTH Stacy and Calvin. In addition, CC your team lead. Add [SPLEAD] to the subject line. 
Intersection selection will come after learning design software and the mainline alignment. 
The design year need to be selection with Caltrans. The budget is dependent on this design year.

Adjorned: 11:30am
